# KRISTAN HILBY

77 Massachusetts Ave. RM 3-153C Cambridge, MA 02139

Email kmhilby@mit.edu
Website kristanhilby.github.io
LinkedIn kristan-hilby
Google Scholar Kristan Hilby

#### **RESEARCH VISION**

My research focuses on finding innovative ways to incorporate compliance into traditionally rigid systems to improve their performance envelope. By systematically integrating and utilizing compliance in the design of machines, I aim to create more adaptable and efficient systems that can perform a wide range of tasks with greater accuracy and precision. Through my research, I aim to develop a deeper understanding of the underlying principles of compliance and how they can be effectively harnessed to improve the functionality of machines across a range of industries and applications.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### **Graduate Student Researcher**

BioInstrumentation Laboratory

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

08/2019 - Current

Cambridge, MA

PhD Research: May 2021 - May 2024 (Anticipated)

- Launched open source stop-rotor aircraft platform using CAD to optimize aerodynamic performance, stability, and control.
- Designed morphing tapered wing capable of reversing leading and trailing edges and subsequently analyzed using CFD and FEA.
- Developed custom flight control system in PX4, incorporating sensor feedback and control algorithms to ensure stable flight across all flight regimes.

M.S. Research: August 2019 - May 2021

- Designed reconfigurable soft robot modules inspired by Yoshimura origami that elongate to 1715% and are driven by reversible electrolysis of water
- Conducted experimental tensile testing and analytical FEA tests to evaluate module's mechanical performance under different loading conditions, including maximum elongation, tensile strength, bending, and buckling.
- Evaluated energetic and compatibility performance of reversible electrolysis of water for untethered pneumatic actuation

## **Undergraduate Student Researcher**

04/2017 - 06/2019

Lipomi Research Group

University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

- Expanded upon methods for quantifying ductile fracture behavior of conjugated semiconducting polymer thin films
- Established effect of conjugation break spacers on poly(3-alkylthiophene) polymers

Summer Undergraduate Research Assistant (UROP)

06/2018 - 08/2018

Collaborative Robotics and Intelligent Systems (CORiS) Group - Cindy Grimm

Oregon State University

Corvallis, OR

- Instrumented door to provide data of robotic grasping including pressure distribution and interaction evolution, improving previous temporal resolution by 3X
- Developed visualization software to reconstruct robot to door interactions in Unity

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

## **Visiting Instructor**

01/2023

American University of Bahrain

Riffa, Bahrain

- Instructed 25 university students on the fundamentals of robotics and prototyping, culminating in independently designed robotic manipulators to sort building blocks.
- Formulated curriculum aimed at enabling creativity in the students including rapid prototyping techniques, overview on artificial intelligence, and creative guidance.

## **Visiting Instructor**

01/2023

Riffa Views International School

Riffa Views, Bahrain

- Instructed 20 high school student on introductory rapid prototyping techniques including CAD, 3D Printing, Laser Machining, and Arduino.
- Crafted hands on curriculum from scratch including design of a pulley system, gravity driven car, ball sorting machine, and arm for throwing balls.

## **Workshop Organizer**

01/2023

Yateem Center Bahrain

Manama, Bahrain

- Instructed 20 students from the ages of 14 to 24 through a two-day free workshop
- Introduced students to computer aided design (CAD) and rapid prototyping methods

**Course Aide** 09/2022 - 12/2022

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

• 6.9970 Academic Job Search

## **Teaching Assistant**

02/2022 - 05/2022

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

• 2.131 Advanced Instrumentation and Measurement

#### **EDUCATION**

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

• **Ph.D.**, Mechanical Engineering [GPA 5.0/5.0]

05/2021 - 05/2024

• **M.S.**, Mechanical Engineering [GPA 4.9/5.0]

(Anticipated)

Thesis: <u>Hydrogen Fuel Cell Driven Origami-Inspired Large</u>

**Elongation Soft Robot Modules** 

08/2019 - 05/2021

University of California, San Diego

06/2016 - 06/2019

• **B.S**, NanoEngineering [GPA 3.96/4.00]

La Jolla, CA

Minor in Electrical Engineering

06/2016 - 06/2019

Graduated Summa Cum Laude

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

## **Conference Proceedings**

- **K. Hilby**, P. Morice, M. Aling, and I. Hunter, "Evaluation and Comparison of Reversible Water Electrolysis as a Means for Pneumatic Actuation," IEEE International Conference on Soft Robots, 2023.
- **K. Hilby**, M. Hughes, and I. Hunter, "Design and Analysis of a Novel Reversible Morphing Airfoil Mechanism," IEEE International Aerospace Conference, 2022.

- **K. Hilby**, V. Padia, and I. Hunter, "Design and Analysis of Origami-Inspired, Large-Elongation, Reconfigurable Soft Robot Module," IEEE International Conference on Soft Robots, 2022.
- **K. Hilby**, J. Morrow, Y. H. Ong, R. Balasubramanian, and C. Grimm, "Instrumented door and drawer for comprehensive robot-object kinematic and force data," IROS Experimental Robotic Grasping and Manipulation Workshop, 2018

## **Journal Articles**

- E. Melenbrink, K. Hilby, K. Choudhary, S. Samal, N.Kazerouni, J. L. McConn, D. Lipomi, and B. Thompson, "Influence of Acceptor Side-Chain Length and Conjugation-Break Spacer Content on the Mechanical and Electronic Properties of Semi-Random Polymers," ACS Applied Polymer Materials, vol. 1, pp. 1107–1117, 5 May 2019, ISSN: 2637-6105.
- E. Melenbrink, **K. Hilby**, M. Alkhadra, S. Samal, D.Lipomi, and B. Thompson, "Influence of Systematic Incorporation of Conjugation-Break Spacers into Semi-Random Polymers on Mechanical and Electronic Properties," ACS Applied Materials and Interfaces, vol. 10, 38 2018, ISSN: 19448252.
- M. Alkhadra, S. Root, **K. Hilby**, D. Rodriquez, F.Sugiyama, and D. Lipomi, "Quantifying the Fracture Behavior of Brittle and Ductile Thin Films of Semiconducting Polymers," Chemistry of Materials, vol. 29, 23 2017, ISSN: 15205002.

#### AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

- MIT 2022 Zakhartchenko Fellowship, awarded \$100,000
- MIT 2021 Meredith Kamm Memorial Award for Excellence in a Woman Graduate Student
- UCSD 2019 Department Away for Outstanding Student in NanoEngineering

## **MENTORSHIP**

**Summary**: 3 undergraduate students, 4 high school students

•	Post Graduate of Bethel University, Matthew Carlson	05/2023 - Present
•	High School Student, Max Hughes	05/2022 - Present
•	High School Student, Jack McCarthy	05/2023 - 08/2023
	High School Student, Arthur Choo	05/2023 - 08/2023
	Undergraduate MIT, Liane Xu	05/2022 - 08/2022
•	Undergraduate MIT, Ryan Xiao	05/2022 - 08/2022
	High School Student, Rushil Sharan	05/2021 - 09/2021
	J ,	

#### OUTREACH AND COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

•	Executive Board, <u>Mechanical Engineering Graduate Associate</u>	04/2022 - Present
	of Women (MEGAWomen)	, .
•	Member, Graduate Student Advisory Group (GradSAGE)	04/2022 - Present
•	Admitted Student Representative, BioInstrumentation Lab	04/2020 - Present
•	Peer Tutor in Robotics and Dynamics Qualifying Exams	09/2021 - 05/2022
	Mentor, <u>Polygence</u>	05/2021 - 09/2021
•	Member, <u>Middle College Effect</u>	08/2014 - 06/2016